<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title> - financial</title>
    <link href="https://blog.wavvel.com/tags/financial/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.wavvel.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-04-06T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.wavvel.com/tags/financial/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>What Is Wealth?</title>
        <published>2025-04-06T00:00:00+07:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-06T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.wavvel.com/posts/life/what-is-wealth/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://blog.wavvel.com/posts/life/what-is-wealth/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is not a financial advice, please consult with your financial advisor before making any financial decisions.
This is a living post and will be updated over-time, it&#x27;s about my perception of wealth. The angle where and how I look at wealth and how to maintain it. I&#x27;m still far away from being wealthy, I&#x27;m grateful that I&#x27;m making progress towards it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-wealth&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#what-is-wealth&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: what-is-wealth&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
What Is Wealth&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wealth is relative, it has different meaning from one person to another.
For me, wealth is about freedom of doing things that I like without worry, without no one forcing me what to do. To achieve that I need to have a balance of: 💪 health, 💰 money(financial strength), and ⏱️  time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;wealth-health&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#wealth-health&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: wealth-health&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Wealth: Health&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health is the most important thing for me, without health I can&#x27;t fully enjoy doing the things that I like,
I cannot work to get paid in which the money can buy time and freedom, what&#x27;s the point of no health?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unfortunately&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; even if I do everything right it&#x27;s not guaranteed that I will be healthy. Regardless, it&#x27;s essential to put health first before anything else. Since health is the base foundation of the wealth, this means the other wealth components are uncertain as well considering uncertainty nature of health. Maintaining health is crucial, definitely please to talk to your doctor, here&#x27;s my take on it:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What goes into the body: eat right while still having time to enjoy the food. I don&#x27;t eat 100% right, maybe just 60-80% of the time, the other 20-40% is for enjoyment balanced with other health component. Dude, I definitely want to enjoy that Ube gelato 🍨!&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exercise: weight lifting and cardio. Being strong and fit reduce the chance of injury and illness, and also help to maintain a healthy weight. I try to do this 2-4 times a week.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to sleep right: still struggling to be consistent on this, generally I try to sleep at least 7 hours a day.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;wealth-money&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#wealth-money&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: wealth-money&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Wealth: Money&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In normal cases money is almost certain in a sense, for example giving value&#x2F;selling to customers will generate money.
Money can definitely buy time and we can be sure that there are 24 hours a day, in which we can buy some part of it, for example hiring maid to do the chores so I can free up 2-3 hour of my time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms money generation, I have 3 main sources of income:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salary: do my best at work and get paid. If possible look for a job with decent health insurance that covers outpatient treatment for the whole family.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investment: basic formula 60-70% on good stocks, the rest goes into low cost bonds index or direct government bonds, rebalance as needed.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Side businesses: profitable and cash generating businesses.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money allocation &lt;strong&gt;structure&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is unique for a specific person but important for you to define what suits you and not to be super rigid, vertically from the bottom up, mine is:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insurance: mainly for protection, covering life insurance, health insurance, critical illness insurance, car insurance.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emergency fund: protection for 12 months of family living expenses, top up regularly as needed. This is the safety net that I can fall back to in case there&#x27;s a need for an urgent cash outflow. Other scenario in case of laid off from work, I can use this fund to cover my living expenses while looking for a new job. I don&#x27;t want to be in a position where I have to take any job just to pay the bills, I want to be able to choose the job that I want with market rate or above salary.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investment: long term investment for retirement.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe it&#x27;s not 100% bullet-proof, there will be cases where things go rough and can break the structure, what I&#x27;m aiming is to have time to recover, survive, and get back on my feet when shit happens.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becareful of money through debt, if leveraged well it can give good returns, but if not it can be a burden. Personally, I prefer not to have any debt at all, I prefer to pay in full unless I&#x27;m certain of the leverage, being &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;posts&#x2F;life&#x2F;debt-free-is-it-worth-it&quot;&gt;debt free is important for me&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as it gives more freedom and more enjoyment in life.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;wealth-time&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#wealth-time&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: wealth-time&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Wealth: Time&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience, time will come eventually as long as health and money are maintained well. Managing time is also crucial for health as well, not enough sleep, too much work, too much playing around can hurt health and money component.
I personally believe time management is relatively simple though not easy, as simple as reducing time on social media will yield extra time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time circles back to wealth, having time means I&#x27;ll be able to do things that I like, play with kids, take care of health (exercise), make more money (study to get better at work, better investment decision, and grow side businesses)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Debt Free, Is It Worth It?</title>
        <published>2025-03-17T00:00:00+07:00</published>
        <updated>2025-03-17T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.wavvel.com/posts/life/debt-free-is-it-worth-it/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://blog.wavvel.com/posts/life/debt-free-is-it-worth-it/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is not a financial advice, please consult with your financial advisor before making any financial decisions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;thinking-about-it&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#thinking-about-it&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: thinking-about-it&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Thinking About It&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I made a decision to pay off all of my debts.
I technically paid off my mortgage in March 2024, it was technically paid off by putting enough money in the autodebit bank account to cover the remaining installment, I just needed to verify
whether the deduction was correct or not once a month, no need to worry about the mortgage anymore. Lastly my car loan last installment was in March 2025, it&#x27;s paid off when I&#x27;m writing this.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decision was not easy but was made relatively quick, only by numbers I would make more money if I invested the money in the stock market or put it in other investment.
Actually I was quite comfortable with the debts, but after thinking for a while I came to conlusion that being debt free is going to be worth it, here&#x27;s why:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&#x27;m able to put more focus only on building wealth. I have more room to take risks, be more bold on good opportunities. Definitely have more courage to average down on good stocks when the market is down.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generally I feel happier without debt, I can&#x27;t measure it but it feels really good! I sleep better as well.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;technically-paying-off-mortgage&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#technically-paying-off-mortgage&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: technically-paying-off-mortgage&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Technically paying off mortgage?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mortgage started in Apr 2018, the mortgage had a fixed rate of 6.5% for 5 years then floating afterwards, in my case it was 13.5%. Yes banks in Indonesia take very high net interest margin.
I think it&#x27;s worth to share that conceptually, mortgage installment amount consists of 2 parts:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Principal amount: this is the amount that will reduce the remaining mortgage amount.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest amount: this goes into the bank pocket.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every installment payment, it will deduct the principal amount and some of it goes to the interest.
Most banks use annuity calculation for mortgage where the interest amount is higher at the beginning of the mortgage period and the principal amount is higher at the end of the period.
In other words your early installment payments will just mostly pay the interest, mostly goes into the bank pocket 💰.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the mortgage deal, 6.5% was quite high compared to other banks, but it had a benefit that the saving account interest rate will match the mortgage rate as well. This is a big deal if you&#x27;re planning to put more money in the saving account.
I got 6.5% interest rate on saving account for the first 5 years, the 6th year it was floating around 13.5% because mortgage interest rate was also 13.5%.
The interest on the saving account is not paid directly into the account balance, rather it deducts the interest from the mortgage installment amount.
Technically the mortgage interest would be 0 if you put enough money in the saving account and all the installment payment will deduct principal, in other words 100% of installment payment will deduct the remaining mortgage amount.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I did to pay off the mortgage was quite simple, I looked up the outstanding mortgage amount then divide the amount by net % after tax on interest, that&#x27;s the amount I need to put in the saving account so that the installment payment would be deduct 100% only to the principal, 0 interest.
Just for example, suppose tax on interest is 20% and my outstanding mortgage is 1000, I would need to put 1000 &#x2F; (1 - 0.2) = 1250 in the saving account.
It will be more than enough to cover the remaining installment.
The reason I like this approach compared to fully settle all at once is because in loan contract there&#x27;s a 3% penalty for early loan settlement, in addition to that if there&#x27;s a super urgent needs for cash I can just withdraw the money from the saving account, though I forbid myself to do that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-forward&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#moving-forward&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: moving-forward&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Moving forward&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having an option to leverage is good, but I think it&#x27;s better to avoid debt if you can.
Debt can give a false sense of security, it can easily confuse you to think that you have the capability to buy things.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the mortgage paid off, I always try to avoid debt. Even if there&#x27;s a 0% installment plan on some of my big purchases, I always choose to pay in full. On the other side paying in full have its own benefits especially for collecting miles, some banks have a policy that you won&#x27;t get the miles if you choose to pay in installment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Melaporkan Asset Rumah dan KPR di SPT Pajak Tahunan Orang Pribadi</title>
        <published>2025-03-10T00:00:00+07:00</published>
        <updated>2025-03-10T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.wavvel.com/posts/life/melaporkan-kpr-di-spt-pajak-tahunan-orang-pribadi/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://blog.wavvel.com/posts/life/melaporkan-kpr-di-spt-pajak-tahunan-orang-pribadi/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Post ini akan ditulis dalam bahasa Indonesia karena memang target audiencenya adalah orang Indonesia.
&lt;strong&gt;Perlu dicatat bahwa jangan mengikuti langkah-langkah yang saya lakukan tanpa berkonsultasi dengan ahli pajak Anda!&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Saya hanya ingin berbagi pengalaman saya saja
dalam melaporkan asset Rumah dan cicilan hutang KPR di SPT Pajak Tahunan Orang Pribadi.
Saya sudah berkonsultasi dengan konsultan pajak saya sebelumnya dan saya ingin sharing saja, semoga informasinya bisa bermanfaat.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;rumah-dan-kpr-di-spt-pajak-tahunan&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#rumah-dan-kpr-di-spt-pajak-tahunan&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: rumah-dan-kpr-di-spt-pajak-tahunan&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Rumah dan KPR di SPT Pajak Tahunan&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secara high level yang perlu dilaporkan di SPT Pajak Tahunan ada 2 component:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rumah dilaporkan pada bagian Harta, dengan kode &lt;code&gt;061 (Tanah dan&#x2F;atau bangunan untuk tempat tinggal)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hutang KPR dilaporkan pada bagian Hutang, dengan kode &lt;code&gt;101 (KPR, Leasing Kendaraan Bermotor, dan sejenisnya)&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nilai asset rumah dilaporkan dengan harga perolehan yang artinya harga&#x2F;uang yang Anda bayarkan untuk mendapatkan asset tersebut.
Nilai hutang KPR bisa dilaporkan mengikuti sisa hutang yang harus dibayarkan ke bank per akhir tahun pajak.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;contoh&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#contoh&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: contoh&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
Contoh&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;kpr-tahun-pertama&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#kpr-tahun-pertama&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: kpr-tahun-pertama&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
KPR: Tahun pertama&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misalnya asumsi sekarang bulan Maret 2025 dan di April 2024 tahun lalu Anda membeli rumah seharga 1 Milyar dengan uang muka 200 juta, sisanya 800 juta dari pinjaman KPR.
Semisal saja didalam KPR terdapat komponen&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biaya administrasi: 10juta&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biaya provisi: 30juta&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biaya bunga (secara total): asumsikan saja 300juta kalau diakumulasi sepanjang tenor pinjaman&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kita bisa hitung jumlah yang harus anda bayarkan ke bank sampai KPR lunas adalah sebesar 800juta + 10juta + 30juta + 300juta = 1.140 juta,
asumsi cicilan 15 juta perbulan mulai dari April 2024, berarti di akhir tahun 2024 sudah membayar total 135 juta.
Maka sisa hutang KPR di akhir tahun 2024 1.140 juta - 135 juta = 1.005 juta, jumlah ini dilaporkan di bagian Hutang dengan kode &lt;code&gt;101&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untuk rumah karena menggunakan konsep harga perolehan, ingat ini jumlah yang dikeluarkan untuk mendapatkan asset tersebut, berarti dilaporkan sebesar DP + nilai KPR = 200juta + 1.140 juta = 1.340 juta di bagian Harta dengan kode &lt;code&gt;061&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.
Dengan begini jumlah penambahan harta rumah, pengurangan cash (karena DP rumah), dan penambahan hutang menjadi seimbang:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harta rumah +1.340 juta&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harta cash: sesuai posisi cash di akhir tahun, harusnya sudah termasuk pengurangan karena membayar DP 200 juta dan cicilan yang dibayarkan 135 juta (Apr - Dec 2024)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hutang KPR +1.005 juta&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secara total, pergerakan nilai harta seimbang dengan pergerakan hutang.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;kpr-tahun-ke-2-dan-seterusnya&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Customize https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;getzola&#x2F;zola&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;components&#x2F;templates&#x2F;src&#x2F;builtins&#x2F;anchor-link.html --&gt;
&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#kpr-tahun-ke-2-dan-seterusnya&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: kpr-tahun-ke-2-dan-seterusnya&quot;&gt;#&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
KPR: Tahun ke-2 dan seterusnya&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tahun selanjutnya pelaporan di SPT Pajak Tahunan cukup mudah:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harta rumah tetap di 1.340 juta (tidak bergerak), asumsi tidak ada renovasi besar maka tidak perlu ditambahkan ke nilai rumah.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nilai hutang KPR berkurang sejumlah cicilan yang dibayar yaitu 1.005 juta - (12 x 15 juta) = 825 juta&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cash gunakan posisi cash di akhir tahun, cash memang selalu bergerak karena pembayaran cicilan KPR dan pastinya ada hal lain juga yang mempengaruhi cashflow.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
