<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title> - war-stories</title>
    <link href="https://blog.wavvel.com/tags/war-stories/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.wavvel.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2023-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.wavvel.com/tags/war-stories/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>War Story: Accidentally Ran A Database Update Without Where Clause</title>
        <published>2023-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://blog.wavvel.com/posts/war-stories/accidentally-ran-a-database-update-without-where-clause/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://blog.wavvel.com/posts/war-stories/accidentally-ran-a-database-update-without-where-clause/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-happened&quot;&gt;What Happened&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2019 I was in a very good mood that the product launch was quite smooth in the past months.
I got report that there were calculation bugs affecting some of the data. The bug was reproducible locally, I skimmed at the code and just kind of knew where the miscalculation happened in the code,
my confident was high and my coffee tasted good on that day!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, I submitted the bug fix to be reviewed and then deployed
the fix to our testing environment. I tested it manually in concurrent to the QA testing process, the fix worked
well on test environment and I deployed it directly to the prod, the fix was confirmed to work on production as well,
I could see incoming data was calculated correctly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the finisher, I move forward to update the old data that was incorrect prior the fix.
I was already in the company network, so I connected to the database through psql
and start writing the update statement. I couldn&#x27;t remember what was going on in my mind but
I typed the closing semicolon as soon as I reached the update statement, I had not typed the filter, it was the
worst thing that could happen.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;update a_table set x = x * 1.1; -- &amp;lt;enter&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#x27;t even notice, looking at my sql statement that I ran, it was kind of hanging there on psql 🤨. It&#x27;s just like your typical query when it&#x27;s processing a lot of data then
it returned the updated rows, showing tens of thousands of data had been updated, this was a small DB, but still tens of thousands is a lot to
fix.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully I was able to pull a quick sql to update all the data again, I was lucky that I applied DML that&#x27;s easy to reverse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;update a_table set x = x &amp;#x2F; 1.1; -- &amp;lt;enter&amp;gt;
&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting cherry on the top, there was no new data coming in. The query worked and
I can still keep my job, also big thanks to my coffee that I made for myself.
Completing the day, I wrote the query with the filter (where clause) first then the DML to complete the day
with a very good lesson that I keep up until now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-went-wrong-and-lesson-learned&quot;&gt;What Went Wrong and Lesson Learned&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the reflection, what I can think of that went wrong:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I should&#x27;ve asked for sql review from my peers.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I should&#x27;ve written the filter first before doing any mutations.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that day on, I always ask for a sql review and always write filter,
this is a very good lesson and I&#x27;m very grateful for it.
I hope you learn something from the war story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
